George W. Winningham Papers
George W. Winningham Papers
1930-1967
Winningham, George W.
0.5 linear ft.
Collection contains clippings regarding George Winningham and several of his writings, including his "Facts and Comments" articles and poetry. In addition, the collection largely contains correspondence between George Winningham, Senator Earle B. Mayfield, Senator Mayfield's son John Mayfield, and various other persons and publishing houses.
3298899
Biographical History
George W. Winningham (1889-unknown) was a Texas legislature (1933-1935), writer, and poet.
Born November 6, 1889, George W. Winningham was elected into the 43rd Texas legislature for the Mexia/Limestone county Jan 10, 1933 - Jan 8, 1935 where he belonged to the Democrat party. He was also a writer for The Groesbeck Journal and The Fredericksburg Radio-Post where he wrote his "Facts and Comments" column. In addition to being a newspaper columnist, Winningham also was a religious poet whose poems were frequently published in local newspapers and Christian bulletins.
George W. Winningham was close friends with former Democrat senator, Earle B. Mayfield (1881-1964) who served in the U.S senate 1923-1929. Senator Mayfield's son John Mayfield was the former curator of the Syracuse University Special Collections in the 1960s.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George W. Winningham Papers contain writings and clippings related to or belonging to George Winningham, but the bulk of the material is his personal and professional correspondence.
Clippings contain various articles written about George W. Winningham or pertain to events that were related to him, such as political affairs or historical preservation efforts.
Correspondence contains letters written between George W.Winningham, Senator Earle B. Mayfield, John Mayfield, The Houston Press, and various other persons (political supporters, friends, collegues, etc.)
Writings contain his "Facts and Comments" column, poetry, and various other articles regarding local history, his Baptist church, and politics.
Miscellaneous contains small maps, a flyer for a political meeting, and pamphlets and articles related to Texas politics written by or related to several of George W. Winningham's collegues.
Arrangement of the Collection
Clippings, correspondence, writings, and miscellaneous are all arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within.
Related Material
For more Earle B. Mayfield correspondence see
John Mayfield Collection Relating to Eugene O'Neill
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Mayfield, Earle Bradford, 1881-1964.; Winningham, George W.; Texas -- Politics and government.; Legislators -- Texas.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Articles.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of George W. Winningham, circa 1965.
Inventory
- Clippings
  - Newspaper, 1933; 1959,; 1964-1966; various articles about George W. Winningham as a poet and legislator, Texas historical figure Leonard Williams, and Fort Parker (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - The Houston Press, 1930-1936; 13 letters (Box 1)
  - Mayfield, Earle B. and Winningham, George W., 1933; 1961-1963; 28 letters (Box 1)
  - Mayfield, John and Winningham, George W., 1963-1965; 21 letters (Box 1)
    various clippings attached; letter 4/18/63 includes 3 blank postcards and "The Comanche Trail and the Massacre at Parker's Fort" by Gene Fallwell; letter 1/22/1964 includes a pamphlet of his poems, "The Fool," "I Know God Understands," and "God is Not Far Away;" letter 6/26/64 contains an article George W. Winningham wrote regarding Earle B. Mayfield; letters 9/28/65 contains "The Prisoners of Perote" by William Preston Stapp and several letters regarding copyright, one of which was written and signed by Lyndon B. Johnson when he was a senator in 1958; letter 11/2/65 contains 4 political pamphlets by Ben B. Hunt; letter 11/1965 contains 2 photographs of George W. Winningham and his wife and a booklet on the history of Texas governors
  - Mayfield, John and Winningham, George W., 1966-1967; undated; various clippings attached; 6 letters (Box 1)
  - Southern Pacific Lines, 1933; "Tracing of Inter-Locking Directorate" - written in pencil by George W. Winningham is his suggestion that some thought this was the cause of the Great Depression (Box 1)
  - Telegrams, 1933; 1938,; 1950; 4 telegrams (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1933-1934; 1959-1965,; undated; various letters from political supporters, friends, collegues and publishers; 53 letters (Box 1)
- Writings
  - "Facts and Comments", 1938; 1965,; undated; political in content, one of which details George W. Winningham's views on communism; 9 articles (Box 1)
  - Poems, undated; "The Fool," "Am I My Brother's Keeper?,"I Know God Understands,"God Is Not Far Away," "Ole Mule's Totin' A Mighty Queer Load," and "Ole Mule's Plumb Tuckered Out" (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938; 1949,; 1965-1966,; undated; views on sales tax, the Texas platform, "Visit with the Poet of Navasota," Praire Grove Baptist church 96th anniversary, letter to the editor on captive John Parker, recognition for best religious editorial of 1948, and story on Limestone county hymn writers (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Political, 1933; 1944,; 1955,; 1965,; undated; small maps, a flyer for a political meeting, and pamphlets and articles related to Texas politics (Box 1)